You know, it's a big privilege for me
إنه لشرف كبير بالنسبة لي العمل بإحدى
the Mascarene Islands in the Indian Ocean.
جزر ماسكارين بالمحيط الهندي.
These islands — Mauritius, Rodrigues, and Réunion —
هذه الجزر — موريشيوس ورودريغز وريونيون —
along with the island of Madagascar,
المحادية لجزيرة مدغشقر،
they are blessed with unique plants
منعَم عليها بنباتات فريدة
found nowhere else in the world.
لا توجد بأي مكان آخر في العالم.
And today I will tell you about five of them
واليوم سأعرفكم على 5 منها
and their particular features
وعن مميزاتها الخاصة
and why these plants are so unique.
وعن السبب في كونها فريدة من نوعها.
Take a look at this plant.
انظروا إلى هذه النبتة.
I call it benjoin in the local vernacular,
أسميها بينجوان باللغة المحلية،
and the botanical name is Terminalia bentzoe,
واسمها العلمي هو تيرميناليا بنزوى،
subspecies bentzoe.
وهو نوع فرعي لبنزوى.
This subspecies is endemic to Mauritius,
يستوطن موريشيوس،
and its particular feature
وميزاتها الخاصة
is its heterophylly.
هو تباين أوراقها.
What do I mean by heterophylly?
ما أقصده بتباين الأوراق،
It's that the same plant
هو أن النبتة الواحدة
has got leaves that are different shapes and sizes.
تملك أوراقا بأشكال وأحجام مختلفة.
Now, these plants have evolved
وقد تطورت هذه النباتات
very far away from the mainland,
بعيدا تماما عن البر الرئيسي،
and within specific ecosystems.
وضمن أنظمة بيئية مستقلة.
Often, these particular features
وكثيرا ما، تطورت تلك المميزات الخاصة
have evolved as a response to the threat
كرد على التهديد
presented by the local fauna,
الذي تشكله الحيوانات المحلية،
in this case, grazing tortoises.
وفي هذه الحالة، السلاحف آكلة العشب.
Tortoises are known to have poor eyesight,
وتعرف السلاحف بضعف بصرها،
and as such, they tend to avoid the plants
وبالتالي، فإنها تميل لتجنب النباتات
they don't recognize.
التي لا تتعرف عليها.
So this evolutionary foil safeguards the plant
لذا فإن هذه الورقة التطورية تحفظ النبتة
against these rather cute animals,
من هذه الحيوانات الظريفة،
and protects it and of course ensures its survival.
وتحميها وبالتالي تضمن بقائها.
Now the question you're probably asking yourself is,
ربما أنكم تتساءلون الآن،
why is she telling us all these stories?
لماذا تحكي لنا كل هذه القصص؟
The reason for that is that we tend to overlook
السبب هو أننا نميل إلى التغاضي
the diversity and the variety of the natural world.
عن تنوع العالم الطبيعي.
These particular habitats are unique
هذه المساكن فريدة من نوعها
and they are host to a whole lot of plants.
لأنها تأوي مجموعة كبيرة من النباتات.
We don't realize how valuable
ونحن لا ندرك مدى أهمية
and how precious these resources are,
وقيمة هذه الموارد،
and yet, through our insouciance,
ومع ذلك، من خلال لامبالاتنا،
we keep on destroying them.
نستمر في تدميرها.
We're all familiar
نحن جميعا اعتدنا التعايش
with the macro impact of urbanization,
مع الأثر الكبير للتمدين،
climate change, resource exploitation,
من تغيير بالمناخ واستغلال للموارد،
but when that one last plant —
لكن عندما يكون الأمر مهما —
or animal for that matter —
لآخر نبتة أو حيوان —
when that very last specimen
عندما يختفي آخر مخلوق من فصيلة ما
has disappeared from the face of this Earth,
من على وجه الأرض،
we would have lost
سنكون قد خسرنا
an entire subset of the Earth's biology,
مجموعة فرعية كاملة من الأحياء على الأرض،
and with it, important plants with medicinal potential
وكذا، نباتات مهمة ذات إمكانيات طبية
or which could have ingredients
أو مكونات ستهم التجميل
nutrition, pharma,
والتغذية وصناعة الأدوية
and even the ethno-veterinary sectors,
وحتى الأدوية الشعبية للحيوانات،
be gone forever.
ستختفي للأبد.
And here we have a very prime example
والمثال الواضح على ذلك هو
of the iconic dodo, which comes from Mauritius,
طائر الدودو الشهير من موريشيوس،
and, of course, we know is now a symbol of extinction.
وبالطبع، الكل يعلم بأنه رمز للانقراض.
We know plants have a fundamental role to play.
كلنا يعلم بأن النباتات تلعب دورا أساسيا.
Well, first of all, they feed us
ابتداء من إطعامنا
and they also give us the oxygen we breathe,
وتزويدنا بالأوكسجين،
but plants are also the source
لكنها أيضا مصدر مهم
of important, biologically active ingredients
لمكونات نشطة بيولوجيا
that we should be studying very carefully,
يجب علينا دراستها بعناية،
because human societies over the millennia,
لأن المجتمعات البشرية خلال آلاف السنين،
they have developed important knowledge,
قامت بتطوير معرفة مهمة،
cultural traditions,
وتقاليد ثقافية،
and important plant-based medicinal resources.
ومصادر مهمة للأدوية المستمدة من النباتات.
Here's a data point:
وهذه بعض البيانات:
1.4 percent of the entire land surface
%1.4 من سطح الأرض
is home to 40 percent of the species of higher plants,
هو موطن ل 40% من النباتات المرتفعة
35 percent of the species of vertebrates,
%35 من الأنواع الفقارية،
and this 1.4 percent
وتمثل نسبة %1.4
represents the 25 biodiversity hotspots in the world,
25 منطقة ذات تنوع بيولوجي بالعالم،
and this 1.4 percent of the entire land surface
وهذه النسبة من سطح الأرض
already provides for 35 percent
تقدم لنا 35%
of the ecosystem services
من خدمات النظام البيئي
that vulnerable people depend on.
التي تعتمد عليها الفئات الضعيفة.
And as you can see,
وكما تشاهدون،
the island of Mauritius
فإن جزيرة موريشيوس
where I work and where I live,
حيث أعمل وأعيش،
belongs to one such biodiversity hotspot,
تنتمي لواحدة من الأماكن الأكثر تنوعا،
and I study the unique plants
وأنا أدرس النباتات الفريدة
on the island for their biomedical applications.
على الجزيرة لاستخداماتها الطبية.
Now, let's go back again
دعوني أعد بكم
to that first plant I showed you,
إلى النبتة الأولى التي أريتكم،
the one, of course, with different-shaped leaves
ذات الأوراق بالأشكال
and different sizes, Terminalia bentzoe,
والأحجام المختلفة، تيرميناليا بنزوى،
subspecies bentzoe,
وهو نوع فرعي لبنزوى.
a plant only found in Mauritius.
نبتة تتواجد فقط بموريشيوس.
Now, the local people,
يستخدم السكان المحليين،
they used a decoction of the leaves
مغلي الأوراق
against infectious diseases.
ضد الأمراض المُعْدِية.
Now our work, that is,
ويتلخص عملنا
the scientific validation of this traditional information,
في التأكيد العلمي للمعلومات التقليدية،
has shown that precisely
التي أظهرت بشكل دقيق أن
that leaf extract shows activity, potent activity,
مستخلص الأوراق أبان عن نشاط قوي
against a wide range of bacteria
ضد طائفة واسعة من البكتيريا
that could be pathogenic to humans.
التي قد تكون ممرضة للبشر.
Now, could this plant be the answer
هل تكون تلك النبتة هي الجواب
to antibiotic resistance?
على مقاومة المضادات الحيوية؟
You know, antibiotic resistance is proving to be
فمقاومة المضادات الحيوية تبرهن عن كونها
a big challenge globally.
تحديا عالمي كبير.
While we may not be sure, one thing is certain:
بينما ما نزال نتخبط، فإن الأمر المؤكد هو:
we will not want this plant to disappear.
أننا لن نرغب في اختفاء هذه النبتة.
But the harsh reality is that
لكن الحقيقة المرة هي أن
this particular plant is in fact
هذه النبتة الفريدة هي في الواقع
considered to be vulnerable
تعتبر من بين النباتات المهددة
in its natural habitat.
في موطنها الطبيعي.
This brings me to another example.
وهذا يقودني إلى مثال آخر.
This bush here is known as baume de l'ile plate
هذه الشجيرة تعرف باسم بوم دو ليل بلات
in the local vernacular.
باللغة المحلية.
The botanical name is Psiadia arguta.
والاسم العلمي هو بسياديا أرغيوتا.
It's a plant which is rare,
وهي نبتة نادرة،
which is endemic to Mauritius.
وتستوطن موريشيوس.
It used to grow on the mainland,
وكانت تنمو بالبر الرئيسي،
but through the sheer pressures of urbanization
لكن بسبب الضغط الكبير للتمدين
has been pushed out of the mainland,
اختفت تقريبا من هناك،
and we've managed to bring it back
وقد نجحنا بإنقاذها
from the brink of extinction
من براثن الانقراض
by developing in vitro plants
من خلال تطويرنا لنباتات مخبرية
which are now growing in the wild.
هي الآن تنمو بالطبيعة.
Now, one thing I must point out straightaway
عَلَيَّ أن أشير لأمر مهم
is that not all plants
إلى أنه لا يمكن تطوير
can be developed in vitro.
جميع النباتات بالمختبر.
While we humans, we are happy in our comfort zone,
بينما نحن البشر فرحون بمنطقتنا المريحة،
these plants also need
فإن هذه النباتات أيضا بحاجة
their ecosystem to be preserved,
لأن يكون نظامها البيئي محميا،
and they don't react — endemic plants
وهي لا تتفاعل — النباتات المستوطنة
don't react to very harsh changes in their ecosystem,
لا تتفاعل مع التغيير الضخم بنظامها البيئي،
and yet we know what are the challenges
مع أننا نعرف نوع التحديات التي يفرضها
that climate change, for example,
التغيير المناخي، مثلا، على هذه النباتات.
Now, the local people again use the leaves
يستخدم السكان المحليين أيضا أوراقها
in traditional medicine
بالطب التقليدي
against respiratory problems.
ضد المشاكل التنفسية.
Now, our preliminary labwork
حيث بينت اختباراتنا الأولية
on the leaf extract has shown
على مستخلص الأوراق
that precisely these leaves contain ingredients
أن هذه الأوراق بالذات تحتوي على مكونات
that are very close, in terms of structures,
تشبه كثيرا، من حيث التركيبة،
chemical structures, to those medicines
التركيبة الكيميائية، لتلك الأدوية
which are sold in the chemist's shop
التي نبيعها بالصيدليات
against asthma.
ضد الربو.
So who knows
من يدري
what humanity will benefit from
ما قد تستفيد منه البشرية
should this plant decide to reveal all its secrets.
إن قررت هذه النبتة الإفصاح عن كل أسرارها.
Now, I come from the developing world
أنا أنتمي للعالم النامي
where we are forever being challenged with this issue
حيث تواجهنا دائما تحديات مشكل
of population explosion.
الانفجار السكاني.
Africa is the continent which is getting younger,
ما زالت أفريقيا تتراجع من حيث السن،
and whenever one talks about population explosion,
عندما نتحدث عن الانفجار السكاني،
one talks about the issue of food security
فإننا نتحدث عن الأمن الغذائي
as being the other side of the same coin.
لأنهما وجهان لعملة واحدة.
Now this plant here, the baobab,
قد تكون هذه النبتة هنا، الباوباب،
could be part of the answer.
جزء من الحل.
It's an underutilized, neglected food plant.
فهي نبتة غذائية قليلة الاستعمال ومهملة.
It defines the landscape of West Africa,
وهي مشهورة بغرب أفريقيا،
where it is known as the tree of life,
حيث تعرف بشجرة الحياة،
and later on I will tell you why
وسأخبركم لاحقا لماذا يعتبرها
the Africans consider it to be the tree of life.
الأفارقة شجرة الحياة.
Now interestingly, there are many legends
المثير بالأمر، أن هناك عدة أساطير
which are associated with this plant.
مرتبطة بهذه النبتة.
Because of its sheer size,
وذلك بسبب حجمها الهائل،
it was meant to be lording over lesser plants,
حيث كان يفترض أن تحكم على النباتات الأخرى،
so God didn't like this arrogance,
لكن الله لم يحب تكبرها،
uprooted it, and planted it upside down,
فاقتلعها وغرسها رأسا على عقب،
hence its particular shape.
مما يفسر شكلها الغريب.
And if you look at this tree again
وإن نظرتم إلى تلك النبتة مرة أخرى
within the African context,
ضمن السياق الأفريقي،
in West Africa, it's known as the palaver tree,
فإنها تعرف بغرب أفريقيا بشجرة اللغو،
because it performs great social functions.
لأنها تؤدي أدوار اجتماعية مهمة.
Now if you have a problem in the community,
إن كان لديكم خلاف في المجتمع،
meeting under the palaver tree
فإن الالتقاء تحت شجرة اللغو
with the chiefs or the tribesmen
مع رؤساء أو رجال القبائل
would be synonymous to trying to find a solution
سيعتبر كمحاولة سلمية لإيجاد الحل
to that particular problem,
لهذا المشكل،
and also to reinforce trust and respect
وكذا لتعزيز الثقة والاحترام
among members of the community.
بين أفراد المجتمع.
From the scientific point of view,
ومن وجهة نظر علمية،
there are eight species of baobab in the world.
هناك 8 أنواع من الباوباب بالعالم.
There's one from Africa,
نوع من أفريقيا،
one from Australia,
نوع من أستراليا،
and six are endemic
و6 منتشرة
to the island of Madagascar.
بجزيرة مدغشقر.
The one I have showed you
النوع الذي أريتكم
is the one from Africa,
هو من أفريقيا،
Adansonia digitata.
الأدنسونيا ديجيتاتا.
Now, the flower, this beautiful white flower,
وتتفتح أزهارها البيضاء الجميلة ليلا،
it opens at night, is pollinated by bats,
وتؤبر بالخفافيش،
and it gives rise to the fruit
فتعطي ثمارا
which is curiously known
معروفة بشكل غريب
as the monkey apple.
باسم تفاح القرود.
The monkeys are not stupid animals.
القرود ليست حيوانات غبية.
They know what's good for them.
فهي تعرف ما يصلح لها.
Now, if you open the fruit of the baobab,
إن فتحتم فاكهة الباوباب،
you'll see a white, floury pulp,
ستشاهدون لب أبيض وطحيني،
which is very rich in nutrients
وهو جد غني بالمغذيات
and has got protein,
ويحتوي على البروتين،
more protein than in human milk.
بروتين أكثر من الحليب البشري.
Yes, you heard right:
نعم، كما تسمعون:
And this is one of the reasons why
وهذا من الأسباب التي
the nutrition companies of this world,
جعلت شركات التغذية في العالم،
they are looking for this fruit to provide
تبحث عن هذه الفاكهة لإنتاج
what we know as reinforced food.
ما نعرفه كأطعمة مدعمة.
The seeds give an oil, a very stable oil
وتمنح البذور زيتًا جدّ مستقر
which is sought after by the cosmetic industry
تسعى صناعة مواد التجميل خلفه
to give to produce body lotions, for example.
لإنتاج مرطبات الجسم، مثلا.
And if you look at the trunk,
وإن نظرتم إلى الجذع،
the trunk, of course, safeguards water,
وهو بالطبع مكان لحفظ الماء،
which is often harvested by a thirsty traveler,
والذي يجمعه المسافر العطش،
and the leaves are used in traditional medicine
وتستخدم الأوراق بالطب التقليدي
against infectious disease.
ضد الأمراض المُعْدِيَة.
Now, you can see now why the Africans consider it
هل اتضح لديكم سبب اعتبارها
to be the tree of life.
من طرف الأفارقة كشجرة الحياة.
It's a complete plant,
إنها نبتة متكاملة،
and in fact, the sheer size of these trees
والحقيقة، أن الحجم الهائل لهذه الأشجار
is hiding a massive potential,
يخفي إمكانات هائلة، ليس فقط
not only for the pharma, nutrition, and the cosmetic industry.
بالصيدلة والتغذية وصناعة مواد التجميل.
What I have showed you here
ما أريتكم هنا
is only the species from Africa,
كان النوع الموجود بأفريقيا فقط،
Adansonia digitata.
الأدنسونيا ديجيتاتا.
We have six species yet in Madagascar,
لدينا 6 أنواع أخرى بمدغشقر،
and we don't know what is the potential of this plant,
ولا نعرف ما هي إمكانات تلك النبتة،
but one thing we know is that the flora
ولكن ما نعرفه هو أن الحياة النباتية
is considered to be threatened with extinction.
هي مهددة بالانقراض.
Let me take you to Africa again,
دعوني آخذكم مجددا إلى أفريقيا،
and introduce you to one of my very favorite,
وأعرفكم على واحدة من النبتات المفضلة لدي،
the resurrection plant.
نبات القيامة.
Now here you'll find
ستلاحظون أنها كالشرير بفيلم ترمنيتر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, this plant here has developed
فقد طورت هذه النبتة
remarkable tolerance to drought,
مقدرة رائعة على تحمل الجفاف،
which enables it to withstand
مما يسمح لها بتحمل
up to 98 percent dehydration over the period of a year
نسبة جفاف تصل إلى 98% خلال السنة
without damage,
دون ضرر،
and yet it can regenerate itself almost completely
بل يمكنها تجديد نفسها بشكل كامل تقريبا
overnight, over 24 hours, and flower.
خلال الليل، في 24 ساعة، وأن تزهر.
Now, us human beings,
ألسنا نحن البشر،
we're always on the lookout for the elixir of youth.
في بحث دائم عن إكسير الشباب.
We don't want to get old, and rightly so.
ولا نريد التقدم بالعمر، وهذا صحيح.
Why should we, especially if you can afford it?
لما علينا ذلك إن كنا نستطيع تفاديه؟
And this gives you an indication
وهذه الصورة تعطيكم لمحة
of what the plant looks like before.
عن شكل النبتة من قبل.
Now, if you are an inexperienced gardener,
إن كنت بستانيًا غير متمرس،
the first thing you'll do when you visit the garden
فإن أول ما ستفعله عند دخولك الحديقة
is to uproot this plant because it's dead.
هو اقتلاع هذه النبتة لأنها ميتة.
But if you water it, this is what you get.
لكن إن سقيتها، هذا ما ستحصل عليه.
Absolutely amazing.
إنها مدهشة للغاية.
Now, if you look at our aging process,
إذا فكرتم جيدا بالشيخوخة،
the aging process is in fact the loss of water
ستجدون أنها عملية فقدان الماء
from the upper epidermis, resulting in wrinkling
من الطبقة العليا للجلد، فتظهر التجاعيد
as we know it, especially women,
وكما نعرف، وخاصة النساء،
we are so conscious of this.
إنه أمر جد مهم.
And this plant, in fact, is giving the cosmetic chemists
والواقع أن هذه النبتة تقدم مكونات جد مهمة
very important ingredients
لكيميائيي التجميل
that are actually finding ways
التي تستطيع أن
to slow down the aging process
تبطئ عملية الشيخوخة
and at the same time reinforce the cells
وفي الوقت نفسه تقوي الخلايا
against the onslaught of environmental toxins.
ضد هجمات سموم بيئتنا.
Now, these four examples
تمثل هذه الأمثلة الأربعة
I have just given you
التي قدمتها لكم للتو
are just a very tiny reminder
تذكير بسيط جدا
as to how our health
عن كون صحتنا
and our survival are closely linked
وبقائنا متوقفين
to the health and the resilience
على صحة ومرونة
of our ecosystem,
نظامنا البيئي،
and why we should be very careful
لذا علينا أن نكون جد حذرين
about preserving biodiversity.
في الحفاظ على التنوع البيولوجي.
Every time a forest is cut down,
ففي كل مرة تدمر فيها غابة،
every time a marsh is filled in,
ويُغْمَر فيها مستنقع،
it is a potential lab that goes with it,
يتم تدمير مختبر،
and which we will never, ever recover.
لن نكتشفه أبدا بعدها.
And I know what I'm talking about,
وأنا أعرف عما أتحدث،
coming from Mauritius and missing the dodo.
لأني من موريشيوس التي فقدت طائر الدودو.
Let me finish with just one last example.
دعوني أختم بآخر مثال.
Conservation issues are normally guided
تركز بالعادة جهود الحماية
towards rare, endemic plants,
على النباتات النادرة والمستوطنة،
but what we call exotic plants,
لكن تلك الأجنبية،
that is, the ones which grow in many different habitats across the world,
التي تنمو في أماكن مختلفة عبر العالم،
they also need to be considered.
يجب أيضا أن تؤخذ في الاعتبار.
You know why? Because the environment plays
هل تعرفون لماذا؟ لأن البيئة تلعب
a very important role
دورا جد مهم
in modifying the composition of that plant.
في تغيير مكونات النبتة.
So let's take a look at this plant here,
دعونا نلقِ نظر على هذه النبتة هنا،
Centella asiatica. It's a weed.
سنتيلا أسياتيكا. هي عشبة ضارة.
We call it a weed.
نقول بأنها كذلك.
Now, Centella asiatica grows across the world
تنمو سنتيلا اسياتيكا بالعالم كله
in many different habitats — in Africa, in Asia —
بعدة بيئات مختلفة — بأفريقيا وآسيا —
and this plant has been instrumental
وكانت هذه النبتة أداة
in providing a solution to that dreadful disease
لتوفير علاج ضد المرض الرهيب
called leprosy in Madagascar in the 1940s.
المسمى بالجذام بمدغشقر في الأربعينيات.
Now, while Centella grows across the world —
وبينما تنمو السنتيلا حول العالم —
in Africa, in Asia — the best quality Centella
بأفريقيا وآسيا — فإن أجودها
comes from Madagascar,
هي تلك في مدغشقر،
because that Centella contains the three vital ingredients
لأنها تحتوي على 3 مكونات حيوية
which are sought after by the pharma
تسعى وراءها شركات الأدوية
and the cosmetic companies.
ومواد التجميل.
And the cosmetic companies are already using it
وتستخدمها شركات مواد التجميل بالفعل
to make regenerating cream.
في صناعة كريم لتجديد البشرة.
Now, there is an ancient saying
هناك قولة قديمة تقول
that for every disease known to mankind,
لكل داء عرفته البشرية،
there is a plant to cure it.
هناك عشبة لعلاجه.
Now, you may not believe in ancient sayings.
قد لا تصدقون أقوال القدماء.
You may think they're obsolete
وقد تعتقدون أنها قديمة
now that our science and technology are so powerful.
وبأن علومنا وتقنياتنا أقوى.
So you may look on Centella as being
قد تعتبرون السنتيلا
an insignificant, humble weed,
نبتة تافهة وضارة
which, if destroyed, won't be missed.
ولن نفتقدها إذا انقرضت.
But you know, there is no such thing as a weed.
لكن كما تعلمون، ليس هناك أشياء كنبتة ضارة.
It's a plant.
إنها نبتة.
It's a living biological lab
إنها مختبر بيولوجي حي
that may well have answers
قد يحتوي على أجوبة
to the question that we may have,
على أسئلة قد نطرحها،
but we have to ensure
لكن علينا التأكد
that it has the right to live.
من حماية حقها في العيش.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.